Now we need a tool to
さて、数えたアイテムの値を保存する
store the value of our counted collectables.
ツールが必要です
And another tool to add
さらに、その値に
to that value as we
取得して数えた値を加算する
collect and count them.
ツールも必要です
Let's add this tool to our
このツールを
PlayerController script.
PlayerController スクリプトに加えましょう
Select the Player game object
Player ゲームオブジェクトを選択し
and open the PlayerController script for editing.
PlayerController スクリプトを開いて編集します
Let's add a private variable
収集したアイテムの総数を記憶する
to hold our count
プライベートの変数を
of collectables we've picked up.
加えましょう
This will be an int,
この変数は int です
as our count will be a whole number
総数は整数で
we won't be collecting partial objects.
オブジェクトを部分的に収集することはないからです
And let's call it Count.
それは、Count という名にしましょう
Type private int count;
private int count;　と入力します
So in our game we will
このゲームでは、最初に
first start with a count of 0.
総数が 0 から始まります
Then we will need to increment
それから、新たにオブジェクトを
our count value by 1
収集するごとに、1 ずつ
when we pick up a new object.
総数を増加させていきます
We need to set our count value to 0.
count の値を 0 に設定します
As this variable is private
この変数はプライベートなので
we don't have any access to it
Inspector では
in the inspector.
アクセスできません
This variable is only available
この変数を使用するのは
for use within this script.
スクリプトからに限られます
And as such we will need to set
そういうわけで、初期値を
it's starting value here in the script.
スクリプトで設定します
There are several ways we can set the starting value
count の初期値を設定するのに
of count but in this assignment
いくつか方法がありますが
we will do it in the Start function.
ここでは Start 関数を使います
In Start set our count
Start 関数内で
to be equal to 0.
count を 0 にします
Type count = 0
count = 0 と入力します
Next we need to add to count
次に、アイテムのゲームオブジェクトを収集したときに
when we pick up our collectable game objects.
総数を増加する必要があります
We will pick up our objects
other ゲームオブジェクトのタグが
in onTriggerEnter2D
Pickup ならば
if the other game object
onTriggerEnter2D で
has the tag Pickup.
そのオブジェクトを取得します
So this is where we add our counting code.
それで、ここに数量計算のコードを加えます
After setting the other game object's
other ゲームオブジェクトの
active state to false
アクティブ状態を
we'll set our new value
false に設定した後
for count to be equal to our
count の更新後の値は
old value plus 1.
古い値プラス 1 になります
We'll type count = count + 1.
count = count + 1; と入力します
There are other ways to add,
Unity のコードで
count up or increment a value
値を合計、増加する方法は
when coding in Unity,
他にもありますが
but this one is very easy to understand
この方法は簡単に理解できるので
and this is the one that we're going to use in this assignment.
ここでは、この方法を使用します
Let's save our script and return to Unity.
スクリプトを保存して Unity に戻りましょう
Now we can store and
これで、総数を保管して
increment our count but we have no
増加することができますが
way of displaying it.
それを表示する方法がありません
It would also be good to display a message
それに、ゲームが終了したときに
when the game is over.
メッセージを表示できたら良いですね
To display text we will be using
テキストを表示するには
Unity's user interface,
Unity のユーザーインターフェイスか
or UI toolset.
UI ツールセットを使います
First let's create a new
最初に Hierarchy の Create メニューから
UI text element
新規の UI Text エレメントを
from the hierarchy's Create menu.
作成しましょう
We seem to have gotten more than we've bargained for.
自分たちが期待した以上のものが手に入ったようです
We don't just have a UI text element
UI Text エレメントだけでなく
but we've also created a
親の Canvas エレメントと
parent canvas element
EventSystem ゲームオブジェクトも
and an EventSystem game object.
作成されました
These are all required
これらはすべて
by the UI toolset.
UI ツールセットに必要です
The single most important thing
これらの追加物について
about these additional items is that
最も重要なことは
all UI elements must
正しく作動するには
be the child of a canvas
すべての UI エレメントは
to behave correctly.
Canvas の子である必要がある、ということです
For more information on the UI tools
UI ツールに関する詳細は
including the canvas and the EventSystem
canvas と EventSystem を含めて
please see the information linked below.
下の情報のリンクをご覧ください
Let's rename the text element
Text エレメントを CountText に
CountText.
名称変更しましょう
With the CountText still highlighted
CountText をハイライトしたままで
place the cursor over the scene view
カーソルを Scene ビューに置き
and press the F key to frame select it.
F キーを押してフレームが選択された状態にします
Let's zoom out so that we can see
キャンバス全体から見た
where the text is positioned
テキストの配置を見るために
relative to the entire canvas.
ズームアウトしましょう
If for some reason this doesn't appear in
何かの理由で中央に表示されない場合は
the centre then we can use the
コンテキスト依存のギアメニューで
context sensitive gear menu
Rect Transform を
to reset the rect transform.
リセットします
Now that our text is centred let's
テキストが中央に配置されたところで
customise this element a bit.
少しカスタマイズしましょう
The default text is a bit dark,
デフォルトのテキストは少し暗いですね
let's make the text colour yellow
テキストを黄色にしましょう
so it's easier to see.
そうすれば見やすいですから
Click on the colour swatch
Color をクリックして
in the colour picker let's set
カラーピッカーで
the red value to 255,
Red 値を 225
the green value to 255 and
Green 値を 225
the blue value to 0.
Blue 値を 0 にします
You can do this by clicking and dragging
クリックしてドラッグするか
or entering the values numerically.
数字を入力して設定します
Close the colour picker.
カラーピッカーを閉じます
Now let's add some placeholder text
プレースホルダーのテキストを加えましょう
and replace the string New Text
文字列 New Text を
with Count Text.
Count Text に置き換えます
Currently the text element
現在、Text エレメントは
is in the centre of the screen
画面の中央にあります
because it's anchored to the
なぜなら、親、つまりここでは
centre of it's parent, which is
キャンバスの中央に
in this case the canvas.
固定されているからです
If is worth noting that the
覚えておくといいですが
transform component on UI elements
UI エレメントのTransform コンポーネントは
is different from that of
Unity の他のゲームオブジェクトの
other game objects in Unity.
それとは異なります
For UI elements the standard
UI エレメントでは
transform has been replaced
標準の Transform は
with the rect transform,
アンカーや配置をはじめとした
which takes in to account
多様な UI システムに必要な
many specialised features
多くの特殊性能を考慮した
necessary for a versatile UI system
Rect Transform に
including anchoring and positioning.
置き換えられています
For more information on the rect transform
Rect Transform に関する詳しい情報は
please see the information linked below.
下のリンクをご覧ください
One of the easiest ways to move
CountText エレメントを左上に移動する
the CountText element in to the
最も簡単な方法の一つは
upper left is to anchor it
キャンバスの中央よりむしろ
to the upper left corner of the canvas
キャンバスの左上の角に
rather than to it's centre.
アンカーすることです
When we re-anchor this text
このテキストエレメントを再度アンカーするときに
element we also want
ピボットと
to set the pivot and the
新しいアンカーに基づく位置も
position based on the new anchor.
設定します
To do this open the
このためには
Anchors And Presets menu
現在のAnchor プリセットを表示している
by clicking on the button displaying
ボタンをクリックして
the current anchor preset.
Anchors Presets メニューを開いてください
Hold down the Shift and Option keys on Mac,
Mac では Shift と Option キーを
or shift and Alt keys on Windows
Windows では Shift と Alt キーを押して
and select the upper left preset by clicking on it.
左上のプリセットを選びクリックします
That's done it.
完了です
Now it looks budged up against
これで、ゲームビューの角に
the corner of the game view.
移動しました
Let's give it some space between the
テキストと画面の端の間に
text and the edges of the screen.
少し隙間を作りましょう
As we're anchored to the upper left
キャンバスの左上の角にアンカーしたので
corner of the canvas and we've
同様に、ピボットも左上の角に
set our pivot to the upper left corner as well.
設定しました
The easiest way to give the text
テキストに少し隙間を作る
a little breathing room is to
もっとも簡単な方法は
change the rect transform's
Rect Transform の
position X and
Pos X と Y の値を
position Y values.
変えることです
In this case an X position of 10
この場合、X 位置を 10
and a Y position of -10
Y 位置を -10 にすると
seem about right.
良いようです
This gives us some room around it
これで少し隙間ができました
yet it's still up and out of the way.
まだ、上すぎて正しい位置ではありませんが
Now let's wire up
さて、総数の値を表示するために
the UI text element to
UI Text エレメントを
display our count value.
設定しましょう
Let's start by opening the
PlayerController スクリプトを開いて
PlayerController script for editing.
編集することから始めましょう
Before we can code anything related to
UI エレメントに関するものをコーディングする前に
any UI elements we need to tell
スクリプトにUI エレメントについて
our script more about them.
説明する必要があります
The details about the UI
UI ツールセットについての詳細は
toolset are held in what's
名前空間と呼ばれるものに
called a namespace.
記憶されています
We need to use this namespace
UnityEngine と System.Collections を使用しているのと同じように
just as we are using
この名前空間を
UnityEngine and System.Collections.
使用する必用があります
So to do this, at the top of our script
そうするには、スクリプトの上の方に
we'll write using UnityEngine.UI
using UnityEngine.UI と入力します
With this in place we can now
これがここにあれば
write our code.
スクリプティングできます
First create a new public
まず、UI Text ゲームオブジェクトの
text variable called CountText
UI Text コンポーネントへの参照を
to hold a reference to the
記憶するために
UI Text component
新しいパブリックのテキスト変数CountText を
on our UI Text game object.
作ります
Type public Text countText
public Text countText と入力します
We need to set the starting value
UI Text のText プロパティーの
of the UI text's Text property.
開始の値を設定する必要があります
WE can do this in Start as well.
これも Start 内でできます
Write countText.text = "Count: " + count.ToString ()
countText.text = "Count: " + count.ToString () と入力します
And we need the parenthesis.
() は必要です
Now this line of code
このコードは count の値を設定した行の
must be written after the line
後に入力するよう
setting our count value
気を付けてください
because Count must have some value
なぜなら count は text に
for us to set the text with.
必要な値を持っているからです
Now we also need to update this text
新しいアイテムを取得したときはいつも
property every time we pick up
この text プロパティーを
a new collectable,
更新しなければなりません
so in OnTriggerEnter
そのため、OnTriggerEnter で
after we increment our count value
count の値を増加した後に
let's write again
もう一度
countText.Text = "Count: " + count.ToString ()
countText.Text = "Count: " + count.ToString () と入力します
We've now written the same line of code
私たちは今までに、同じスクリプト内に
twice in the same script.
2 回、同じコードを入力しました
This is generally bad form.
こういう形は一般的には良くありません
One way to made this a little more elegant
これを少しすっきりさせるには
is to create a function that
ある場所で作業を行う関数を作っておき
does the work in one place
必要な時にいつでも
and we simply call this function
この関数を
every time we need it.
呼び出す方法です
Let's create a new function called
では、SetCountText という
SetCountText.
新しい関数を作成しましょう
Type void SetCountText
void SetCountText と入力し
followed by an empty set of parenthesis
その後に空の () と
and an empty set of brackets.
空の {} をつけます
Now let's move one
では、このコードの 1 つを
instance of this line of code
カット＆ペーストで
in to the function by cutting and pasting it.
この関数に移しましょう
And in it's place let's put
そして、それがあった場所に
a line of code simply calling the function.
作った関数を呼び出すコードを入力します
Finally let's replace the
最後に、もう 1 つの行も
other line with the function call as well.
呼び出し関数に置き換えます
Save and return to Unity.
保存して Unity に戻ります
Now we see our PlayerController script
PlayerController スクリプトに
has a new text property.
新しいテキストプロパティーがあります
We can associate a reference to our
CountTextゲームオブジェクトを
Count Text simply by dragging and dropping
このスロットに単にドラッグ & ドロップすることで
the CountText game object
Count Text への参照に
on to this slot.
関連付けできます
Unity will find the text component
Unity はゲームオブジェクトの
on the game object and correctly
Text コンポーネントを探して
associate the reference.
正しく参照と関連付けします
Let's save the scene and play.
シーンを保存して再生しましょう
Great, now not only do we collect
いいですね。今ではオブジェクトを
these objects but we can count them now.
集めるだけでなく数えられるようになりました
Let's exit play mode.
プレイモードを閉じましょう
We need to display a message
アイテムをすべて収集したときに
when we have collected all of the pickups.
メッセージを表示する必要があります
To do this we will need another
そうするには、もう 1 つ
UI text object.
UI Text オブジェクトが必要です
Again, using the hierarchy's Create menu
もう 1 度 Hierarchy の Create メニューを使って
make a new UI text game object.
新しい UI Text ゲームオブジェクトを作ります
Rename it WinText.
それを WinText という名にします
Note how the new UI text element is
新しい UI Text エレメントがどのようにして
automatically added to our canvas.
自動的に Canvasに加えられたかに気を付けてください
We want this text to display
このテキストをゲーム空間の
in the centre of the game space
中央の少し上に表示します
but up a little bit so it doesn't
そうすれば Player ゲームオブジェクトを
cover the Player game object.
隠さずにすみます
To do this let's adjust the rect transform's
そうするには Rect Transform のPos Y エレメントを
position Y element as by default
UI Text エレメントが デフォルトで
this UI text element is anchored
canvas の中央にアンカーされるよう
to the centre of the canvas.
調整しましょう
A value of about 75 feels good.
75 あたりが適切なようです
Let's also adjust the
Text コンポーネントの
paragraph alignment
Paragraph のAlignment も
in the text component.
調整しましょう
Next let's adjust the colour
次に、色を調整して
and set it to the same yellow
以前の Text エレメントに使用した
we used for our previous text element.
黄色に設定します
Let's make the text a little larger
フォントサイズを 24 にして
by setting the font size to 24.
テキストを少し大きくしましょう
Finally let's add some place holder text
最後に、プレースホルダーのテキストを加え
and replace the string New Text
文字列 New Text を Win Text　に
with Win Text.
置き換えましょう
Let's save the scene and swap
シーンを保存して
back to our scripting editor.
スクリプトエディターに戻りましょう
We need to add a reference for
この UI Text エレメントの参照を
this UI text element.
加える必要があります
Let's create a new public text
新しいパブリックの Text の変数を作り
variable and call it WinText.
WinText と呼びましょう
Type public Text winText.
public Text winText と入力します
Now let's set the starting value
WinText の text プロパティーの
for WinText's text property.
最初の値を設定します
This is set to an empty string
これは空の文字列にするか
or two double quote marks
何も中に入ってない
with no content.
“” マークにします
This text property will start empty
この Text プロパティーは空で始まります
then in the SetCountText function
それから、SetCountText 関数に
let's write if count is greater than or equal to 12,
以下を入力します。「count が 12 より大きい、または等しければ、」
which is the total number of objects we have
12 はゲーム内で収集できる
in the game to collect,
オブジェクトの総数です
then our winText.Text
「winText.Text は
equals You Win!
You win! に等しい」
Type if count is greater than or equal to 12
If (count >= 12)
winText.Text = YouWin!
winText.Text = “YouWin!”; と入力します
Let's save this script and return to Unity.
このスクリプトを保存して Unity に戻ります
Again on our Player our player
ここでも Player 上の Player Controllerに
controller has a new UI text property.
新しい UI Text プロパティーが表示されています
We can associate the component again
ここでもまた、WinText ゲームオブジェクトを
by dragging the WinText
新しいスロットにドラッグして
game object in to the new slot.
コンポーネントの関連付けができます
Let's save the scene and play.
シーンを保存して再生しましょう
So we're picking up our game objects,
ゲームオブジェクトを収集して
we're counting our collectables
それを数え
and we win!
勝ちました！
And as we can see when we have
さらに、12 のオブジェクトを全部集めると
collected 12 objects we display the You Win! text.
「You Win!」(勝利！) のテキストが表示されます
In the next and last assignment
次回このシリーズ最後のレッスンでは
of this series we will build
スタンドアロンプレイヤーを使って
the game and deploy it
ゲームをビルドして
using a stand alone player.
デプロイします